Finding Aid for St. Thomas Evangelical Lutheran Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records, 1844-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Thomas Evangelical Lutheran Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records 1844-2000
St. Thomas Evangelical Lutheran Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
1.5 linear foot
2008004 Ba 2
St. Thomas Evangelical Lutheran Church, founded in 1842 in Freedom Township, near Ann Arbor, Michigan; record group includes church registers, financial records, administrative materials, and other subject files.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the church and was received from Rev. Charles Schulz (donor no. 9935 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research. Access to three volumes of early church registers is restricted for preservation reason. Microfilm copies are available for use.
St. Thomas Evangelical Lutheran Church was founded in 1842 by German settlers in Freedom Township, Washtenaw County, Michigan under the leadership of Frederich Schmid, the first German missionary sent to America from the Basel Mission Institute in Switzerland. (Friedrich Schmid's records are also located at the Bentley Historical Library.). The current church building was dedicated in 1874 and is located 1/2 mile east of the original site. St. Thomas was the first church in Michigan to join the Lutheran Church, Missouri Synod.
At the time of this writing St. Thomas Evangelical Lutheran Church is an active congregation led by Pastor Rev. Charles Schulz. St. Thomas recently celebrated its 165th Anniversary.
The St. Thomas Evangelical Lutheran Church record group includes church registers containing family and membership information; financial ledgers; constitutions and by-laws; anniversary and celebratory materials; files relating to church organizations; and photographs of church building.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Church history.; German Americans--Michigan.; Freedom (Mich.: Township)--Church history.; Lutheran Church--Missouri Synod--Michigan--Freedom (Township); Lutheran Church--Missouri Synod--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Freedom (Township); Schmid, Friedrich, 1807-1883; St. Thomas Evangelical Lutheran Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Historical and Genealogical
  The Historical and Genealogical series (0.75 linear feet) contains Church Registers from the 19th and 20th Centuries. Much of the older material is in German. The Church Registers and Family Register contain information which genealogists will find valuable concerning German settlers in Freedom Township and Ann Arbor, Michigan. The financial ledgers in this series contain church membership lists by way of a record of tithes (collections). Some early registers were transcribed and translated.
  - Kirchen Buch (church register)
    - Originals
      - 1867-1912
        [restricted access, use microfilm copy]
      - 1910-circa 1955
    - Microfilm Copy (mf533c)
      - 1867-1912 (Reel 1)
      - 1910-circa 1955 (Reel 1)
  - Confirmands 1869-1920 (not inclusive) and Membership List, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Familien Register der Thomas Gemeinde in Freedom circa 1840-1903
    (includes register of families, ca. 1840s-ca. 1900 and school, 1897-1903)
    - Original
    - Microfilm copy (Reel 1)
  - Financial Ledgers / Collections Rosters
    - 1844-1852 (Box 1)
    - 1847, 1856, 1859, 1863, 1867 undated (Box 1)
    - 1885-1893 (Box 1)
    - 1917-1923 (Box 1)
    - 1929-1944 (not inclusive), 1957, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - 1967-1972 (Box 1)
  - Funeral Service / Obituary Notes: (Box 1)
    (Mrs. Martha Anna Hildinger (1889-1964), Norman Albert Gross (1917-1964), Carl Haab (1891-1964)
  - Historical Notes (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1874, 1959, 1973, 1992 (150th Anniversary), Undated (Box 1)
  - Photocopy of a record book (possibly St. Thomas) dating from the mid 19th century (Box 1)
  - Photographs (27) and Photographic Slides 1990 (Box 1)
  - Transcriptions and Translations of Selected Historical Records and Research Queries (Box 1)
- Organizational
  The Organizational series (1 linear foot) contains correspondence and ephemera concerning St. Thomas's 125th, 130th, and 140th Anniversary celebrations, drafts and revisions of the church's constitution, and meeting minutes.
  - 125th Anniversary 1967, 130th Anniversary, 1972, and 140th Anniversary, 1982 Minutes, Correspondence, and Ephemera (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Circuit Sunday School Association 1963-1967 (Box 1)
  - Constitution and By-Laws
    - Proposed Amendments 1959 (Box 1)
    - Committee Minutes 1963 (Box 1)
    - Constitution and By-Laws 1969-2003 (Box 1)
    - Constitution, Drafts and Revisions 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - Finances 1972-1987 (Box 1)
  - Ladies Aid
    - 1917-1950 (Box 1)
      (in German and English)
    - 1951-2000, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Loose ephemera and correspondence (Box 2)
  - Lutheran Witness Subscriptions 1997-1998 (Box 2)
  - Minutes 1867-1964 (Box 2)
  - Parochial Reports 1938-1940, 1955-1962 (Box 2)
  - "Parish Renewal Through Education" Secretary's Reports 1970 (Box 2)
  - Pastoral Installations: John W. Ribar 1965 Daniel Lloyd Mattson, 1969 John G. Riske, 1985, and John Kayser, 1995; Richard W.T. Bierlein Obituary and Funeral Service, 1962 and John W. Ribar Resignation, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Sunday School 1967-1975 (Box 2)
  - Walther League and Youth Association 1963-1972 (Box 2)
    (incl. a Walther League public service announcement distributed on a 7" vinyl record, 33 1/3 rpm)
  - Walther League Binder, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Young People's Society 1933-1942, 2 folders (Box 2)